<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<!--
This file is used by both mandos(8) and mandos.conf(5), since these
options can be used both on the command line and in the config file.

It is also used for some texts by mandos-client(8mandos).
-->

<section>
  <title/>
  
  <para id="interface">
    If this is specified, the server will only announce the service
    and listen to requests on the specified network interface.
    Default is to use all available interfaces.  <emphasis
    >Note:</emphasis> a failure to bind to the specified
    interface is not considered critical, and the server will not
    exit, but instead continue normally.
  </para>
  
  <para id="address">
    If this option is used, the server will only listen to the
    specified IPv6 address.  If a link-local address is specified, an
    interface should be set, since a link-local address is only valid
    on a single interface.  By default, the server will listen to all
    available addresses.  If set, this must normally be an IPv6
    address; an IPv4 address can only be specified using IPv4-mapped
    IPv6 address syntax: <quote><systemitem class="ipaddress"
    >::FFFF:192.0.2.3</systemitem ></quote>.  (Only if IPv6 usage is
    <emphasis>disabled</emphasis> (see below) must this be an IPv4
    address.)
  </para>
  
  <para id="port">
    If this option is used, the server will bind to that port. By
    default, the server will listen to an arbitrary port given by the
    operating system.
  </para>
  
  <para id="debug">
    If the server is run in debug mode, it will run in the foreground
    and print a lot of debugging information.  The default is to
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> run in debug mode.
  </para>
  
  <para id="priority">
    GnuTLS priority string for the <acronym>TLS</acronym> handshake.
    The default is <quote><literal
    >SECURE256:!CTYPE-X.509:+CTYPE-OPENPGP:+SIGN-RSA-SHA224</literal></quote>.
    See <citerefentry><refentrytitle
    >gnutls_priority_init</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> for the syntax.
    <emphasis>Warning</emphasis>: changing this may make the
    <acronym>TLS</acronym> handshake fail, making server-client
    communication impossible.
  </para>
  
  <para id="servicename">
    Zeroconf service name.  The default is
    <quote><literal>Mandos</literal></quote>.  This only needs to be
    changed if for some reason is would be necessary to run more than
    one server on the same <emphasis>host</emphasis>.  This would not
    normally be useful.  If there are name collisions on the same
    <emphasis>network</emphasis>, the newer server will automatically
    rename itself to <quote><literal>Mandos #2</literal></quote>, and
    so on; therefore, this option is not needed in that case.
  </para>
  
  <para id="dbus">
    This option controls whether the server will provide a D-Bus
    system bus interface.  The default is to provide such an
    interface.
  </para>
  
  <para id="ipv6">
    This option controls whether the server will use IPv6 sockets and
    addresses.  The default is to use IPv6.  This option should
    <emphasis>never</emphasis> normally be turned off, <emphasis>even in
    IPv4-only environments</emphasis>.  This is because <citerefentry>
    <refentrytitle>mandos-client</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8mandos</manvolnum></citerefentry> will normally use
    IPv6 link-local addresses, and will not be able to find or connect
    to the server if this option is turned off.  <emphasis>Only
    advanced users should consider changing this option</emphasis>.
  </para>
  
  <para id="restore">
    This option controls whether the server will restore its state
    from the last time it ran.  Default is to restore last state.
  </para>
  
  <para id="statedir">
    Directory to save (and restore) state in.  Default is
    <quote><filename
    class="directory">/var/lib/mandos</filename></quote>.
  </para>
  
  <para id="socket">
    If this option is used, the server will not create a new network
    socket, but will instead use the supplied file descriptor.  By
    default, the server will create a new network socket.
  </para>
  
  <para id="foreground">
    This option will make the server run in the foreground and not
    write a PID file.  The default is to <emphasis>not</emphasis> run
    in the foreground, except in <option>debug</option> mode, which
    implies this option.
  </para>
  
</section>
