<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<!--
This file is used by both mandos(8) and mandos.conf(5), since these
options can be used both on the command line and in the config file.
-->

<section>
  <title/>
  
  <para id="interface">
    If this is specified, the server will only announce the service
    and listen to requests on the specified network interface.
    Default is to use all available interfaces.  <emphasis
    >Note:</emphasis> a failure to bind to the specified
    interface is not considered critical, and the server does not
    exit, but will instead continue normally.
  </para>
  
  <para id="address">
    If this option is used, the server will only listen to the
    specified IPv6 address.  If a link-local address is specified, an
    interface should be set, since a link-local address is only valid
    on a single interface.  By default, the server will listen to all
    available addresses.  If set, this must be an IPv6 address; an
    IPv4 address can only be specified using IPv4-mapped IPv6 address
    syntax: <quote><systemitem class="ipaddress"
    >::FFFF:192.0.2.3</systemitem ></quote>.
  </para>
  
  <para id="port">
    If this option is used, the server will bind to that port. By
    default, the server will listen to an arbitrary port given by the
    operating system.
  </para>
  
  <para id="debug">
    If the server is run in debug mode, it will run in the foreground
    and print a lot of debugging information.  The default is to
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> run in debug mode.
  </para>
  
  <para id="priority">
    GnuTLS priority string for the TLS handshake with the clients.
    The default is
    <quote><literal>SECURE256:!CTYPE-X.509:+CTYPE-OPENPGP</literal></quote>.
    See <citerefentry><refentrytitle>gnutls_priority_init
    </refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> for the
    syntax.  <emphasis>Warning</emphasis>: changing this may make the
    TLS handshake fail, making communication with clients impossible.
  </para>
  
  <para id="servicename">
    Zeroconf service name.  The default is
    <quote><literal>Mandos</literal></quote>.  This only needs to be
    changed this if it, for some reason, is necessary to run more than
    one server on the same <emphasis>host</emphasis>, which would not
    normally be useful.  If there are name collisions on the same
    <emphasis>network</emphasis>, the newer server will automatically
    rename itself to <quote><literal>Mandos #2</literal></quote>, and
    so on; therefore, this option is not needed in that case.
  </para>
  
</section>
